<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>trojita.desktop</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-2.0+</project_license>
  <name>Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="ar">تروجيتا</name>
  <name xml:lang="ast">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="bs">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="ca">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="ca-valencia">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="cs">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="da">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="de">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="el">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="en-GB">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="es">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="fi">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="gl">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="hu">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="it">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="ko">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="nds">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="nl">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="pl">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt-BR">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="sk">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="sv">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="uk">Trojitá</name>
  <name xml:lang="x-test">xxTrojitáxx</name>
  <summary>IMAP E-mail Client</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ar">عميل بريد IMAP إلكترونيّ</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="bs">IMAP klijent za elektronsku poštu</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca">Client de correu electrònic IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca-valencia">Client de correu electrònic IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="cs">Poštovní klient pro IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="da">E-mail-klient til IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">IMAP-E-Mail-Programm</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="el">IMAP εφαρμογή ηλεκτρονικής αλληλογραφίας</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="en-GB">IMAP E-mail Client</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="es">Cliente de correo IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fi">IMAP-sähköpostiohjelma</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="gl">Cliente de correo IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="hu">IMAP e-mail kliens</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="it">Client di posta elettronica IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ko">IMAP 이메일 클라이언트</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nds">IMAP-Nettpostprogramm</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nl">IMAP-E-mailclient</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pl">Klient pocztowy IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt">Cliente de E-mail por IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt-BR">Cliente de e-mail IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sk">IMAP e-mailový klient</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sv">IMAP e-postprogram</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="uk">Клієнтська програма для роботи з електронною поштою IMAP</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="x-test">xxIMAP E-mail Clientxx</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Trojitá is an email program ("client") specialized in giving fast and efficient access to mailboxes over the IMAP protocol.
      An IMAP mail server stores messages and allows clients to fetch messages to the local computer when asked for.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">تروجيتا هو برنامج ("عميل") بريد إلكترونيّ مخصّص للسّرعة والنّفاذ الفعّال إلى صناديق البريد عبر ميفاق IMAP. خادوم بريد IMAP يخزّن الرّسائل ويسمح للعملاء بجلبها إلى الحاسوب المحليّ عند سؤالهم عنها.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Trojitá je email program ("klijent") specijaliziran u davanju brzog i efikasnog pristupa poštanskim kutijama preko IMAP protokola. IMAP poštanski server pohranjuje poruke i dopušta klijentima da uhvate poruke na lokalnom računaru kada zatraže.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">Trojitá és un programa de correu electrònic («client») que s'especialitza a donar un accés ràpid i eficient a les bústies de correu a través del protocol IMAP. Un servidor de correu IMAP emmagatzema els missatges i permet als clients obtenir-los des de l'ordinador local.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">Trojitá és un programa de correu electrònic («client») que s'especialitza a donar un accés ràpid i eficient a les bústies de correu a través del protocol IMAP. Un servidor de correu IMAP emmagatzema els missatges i permet als clients obtindre-los des de l'ordinador local.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Trojitá er et e-mail-program ("klient") der er specialiseret i at give hurtig og effektiv adgang til postkasser over IMAP-protokollen. En IMAP-mailserver lagrer breve og lader klienter hente breve til den lokale computer når der er behov for det.</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Η Trojitá είναι ένα πρόγραμμα ηλεκτρονικού ταχυδρομείου («εφαρμογή-πελάτης») με ειδικότητα τη γρήγορη και αποτελεσματική πρόσβαση σε γραμματοκιβώτια με το πρωτόκολλο IMAP. Ένας διακομιστής IMAP ηλεκτρονικής αλληλογραφίας αποθηκεύει τα μηνύματα και επιτρέπει στις εφαρμογές να τα μεταφέρουν στον τοπικό υπολογιστή όταν τους ζητηθεί.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">Trojitá is an email program ("client") specialised in giving fast and efficient access to mailboxes over the IMAP protocol. An IMAP mail server stores messages and allows clients to fetch messages to the local computer when asked for.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">Trojitá es un programa de correo electrónico («cliente») especializado en dar un acceso rápido y eficiente a los buzones de correo sobre el protocolo IMAP. Un servidor de correo IMAP almacena los mensajes y permite a los clientes extraerlos en un sistema local cuando se le pida.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Trojitá on sähköpostiohjelma (”-asiakas”), joka on erikoistunut nopeaan ja tehokkaaseen IMAP-yhteyskäytännön yli tapahtuvaan käyttöön. IMAP-postipalvelin tallentaa viestit ja antaa asiakkaiden noutaa viestejä paikalliselle tietokoneelle pyydettäessä.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">Trojitá é un programa de correo electrónico ("cliente") especializado en fornecer acceso rápido e eficiente a caixas de correo mediante o protocolo IMAP. Os servidores de correo de IMAP almacenan mensaxes e permiten que os clientes obteñas as mensaxes cando as solicitan.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Trojitá è un programma di posta elettronica («client») specializzato nel fornire, tramite protocollo IMAP, un accesso rapido ed efficiente alle caselle di posta. Un server di posta IMAP conserva i messaggi e permette ai client di scaricare, a richiesta, i messaggi nel computer locale.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">Trojitá는 IMAP 프로토콜을 사용하여 편지함에 빠르고 효율적으로 접근할 수 있도록 하는 도구입니다. IMAP 메일 서버에는 메시지가 저장되며 필요할 때 클라이언트에서 로컬 컴퓨터로 가져올 수 있습니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Trojitá is een e-mailprogramma ("client") gespecialiseerd in het geven van snelle en efficiënte toegang tot e-mailboxen over het IMAP-protocol. Een IMAP-e-mailserver slaat berichten op en biedt clients de mogelijkheid om berichten naar de lokale computer te halen wanneer dat wordt gevraagd.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Trojitá jest programem pocztowym ("klientem") specjalizującym się w zapewnianiu szybkiego i wydajnego dostępu do skrzynek pocztowych przez protokół IMAP. Serwer pocztowy IMAP przechowuje wiadomości i umożliwia klientom pobieranie wiadomości na komputer lokalny wtedy, gdy tego chcą.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O Trojitá é um programa ("cliente") de e-mail especializado em dar um acesso rápido e eficiente às caixas do correio através do protocolo IMAP. Um servidor de correio IMAP guarda as mensagens e permite aos clientes transferir as mensagens para o computador local, sempre que tal for pedido.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">O Trojitá é um programa de e-mail ("cliente"), especializado em fornecer acesso rápido e eficiente às caixas do correio através do protocolo IMAP. Um servidor de e-mail IMAP armazena as mensagens e permite que os clientes as transfiram as para o computador local quando solicitado.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Trojitá je e-mailový program ("klient") špecializovaný na rýchly a efektívny prístup k mailboxom cez protokol IMAP. Poštový server IMAP ukladá správy a umožňuje klientom naťahovať správy do miestneho počítača na požiadanie.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Trojitá är ett e-postprogram ("klient") specialiserat på att ge snabb och effektiv åtkomst till brevlådor via IMAP-protokollet. En IMAP e-postserver lagrar brev och låter klienter hämta breven till den lokala datorn när de efterfrågas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Trojitá — програма для роботи з електронною поштою («клієнт»), що спеціалізується на наданні швидкого та ефективного доступу до поштових скриньок за допомогою протоколу IMAP. Самі повідомлення електронної пошти зберігаються на поштовому сервері IMAP, клієнтська програма отримує повідомлення на локальному комп’ютері, коли у цьому виникає потреба.</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxTrojitá is an email program ("client") specialized in giving fast and efficient access to mailboxes over the IMAP protocol. An IMAP mail server stores messages and allows clients to fetch messages to the local computer when asked for.xx</p>
    <p>
      It prioritizes efficiency, speed and open standards above other goals.
      Trojitá also aims to be multi-platform, and functions well on everything from big desktop computers to small cellphones.
      Trojitá is a stand-alone program, not part of a "personal information manager" suite.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">يعطي تروجيتا الأولويّة إلى الكفاءة، والسّرعة والمعايير الحرّة على الأهداف الأخرى. يهدف أيضًا إلى أن يكون عابرًا للمنصّات وأن يعمل عملًا جيّدًا على أيّ شيء، من حواسيب سطح المكتب الكبيرة إلى الهواتف الصّغيرة. تروجيتا برنامج مستقلّ، وليس جزء من طقم "مدير معلومات شخصيّة".</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Daje prednost efikasnosti, brzini i otvorenim standardima ispred drugih ciljeva. Trojitá također teži da bude višestruka platforma i da dobro funkcioniše na svemu, od velikih desktop računara do malih mobilnih uređaja. Trojitá je nezavisan program, nije dio "lično-informacijskog menadžerskog" paketa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">Dóna prioritat a l'eficiència, la velocitat i els estàndards oberts per sobre d'altres objectius. Trojitá també aspira a ser multiplataforma, i funciona bé arreu, des d'ordinadors d'escriptori grans a telèfons mòbils petits. Trojitá és un programa independent, no forma part d'una suite de «gestor de la informació personal» (PIM).</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">Dóna prioritat a l'eficiència, la velocitat i els estàndards oberts per sobre d'altres objectius. Trojitá també aspira a ser multiplataforma, i funciona bé arreu, des d'ordinadors d'escriptori grans a telèfons mòbils petits. Trojitá és un programa independent, no forma part d'una suite de «gestor de la informació personal» (PIM).</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Den prioriterer effektivitet, hastighed og åbne standarder over andre mål. Trojitá prøver også at virke på flere platforme, og fungere godt på alt fra store desktop-computere til små mobiltelefoner. Trojitá er et selvstændigt program, det er ikke del af suite til håndtering af personlig information.</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Δίνει προτεραιότητα σε αποτελεσματικότητα, ταχύτητα και στα ανοιχτά πρότυπα πάνω απ' όλα. Η Trojitá επίσης στοχεύει να έχει υλοποίηση για πολλές πλατφόρμες και να λειτουργεί καλά σε οτιδήποτε από μεγάλους υπολογιστές γραφείου μέχρι μικρά κινητά τηλέφωνα. Η Trojitá είναι ένα ανεξάρτητο πρόγραμμα, όχι τμήμα κάποιας σουίτας «διαχείρισης προσωπικών πληροφοριών».</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">It prioritises efficiency, speed and open standards above other goals. Trojitá also aims to be multi-platform, and functions well on everything from big desktop computers to small cellphones. Trojitá is a stand-alone program, not part of a "personal information manager" suite.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">Prioriza la eficiencia, la velocidad y los estándares abiertos por encima de otros objetivos. Trojitá también pretende ser multiplataforma y funciona bien en cualquier equipo, desde los de escritorio hasta los teléfonos móviles más pequeños. Trojitá es un programa independiente que no forma parte de ningún sistema de «gestión de información personal».</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Ohjelmassa kaikkien muiden päämäärien edellä ovat tehokkuus, nopeus ja avoimet standardit. Trojitá pyrkii myös monialustaisuuteen, ja se toimii kaikkialla perinteisistä pöytäkoneista matkapuhelimiin. Trojitá on itsenäinen ohjelma eikä osa mitään ”henkilökohtaisen tiedon hallinnan” ohjelmistoa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">Dálle prioridade á eficiencia, a velocidade e os estándares abertos por riba de calquera outra cousa. Trojitá tamén pretende funcionar en calquera plataforma, e intégrase ben tanto en pantallas grandes como en pantallas de teléfono. Trojitá é un programa independente que non forma parte de ningunha colección de programas de xestión de información persoal (PIM).</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Esso dà priorità, tra le altre cose, all'efficienza, la velocità e gli standard aperti. Trojitá vuole anche essere multi-piattaforma, e funziona bene sia sui grandi computer da tavolo, sia sui cellulari. Trojitá è un programma indipendente, non fa parte di una suite di «gestione personale delle informazioni».</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">효율성, 속도, 표준 준수를 목표로 합니다. Trojitá는 데스크톱부터 스마트폰까지 여러 플랫폼에서 작동하는 것을 목표로 합니다. Trojitá는 "개인 정보 관리자" 모음과 개별적으로 작동하는 독립 프로그램입니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">De prioriteit ligt op efficiëntie, snelheid en open standaarden boven andere doelen. Trojitá richt zich ook op multi-platform en functies die het goed doen op alles vanaf grote desktopcomputers tot kleine telefoons. Trojitá is een alleenstaand programma, is geen onderdeel van een "persoonlijke informatebeheerder" suite.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Przedkłada wydajność, szybkości i otwarte standardy nad innymi celami. Trojitá zamierza także być wielo-platformowym programem i działa dobrze na wszystkim począwszy od dużych komputerów biurkowych po małe telefony komórkowe. Trojitá jest samodzielnym programem, nie częścią pakietu "zarządzania informacjami osobistymi".</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">Dá prioridade à eficiência, velocidade e a normas abertas, acima de todos os outros objectivos. O Trojitá também pretende ser multi-plataforma, funcionando bem em tudo, desde computadores grandes até telemóveis pequenos. O Trojitá é um programa autónomo, não fazendo parte de um pacote de "gestão de informações pessoais".</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">Ele prioriza a eficiência, velocidade e os padrões abertos, acima de todos os outros objetivos. O Trojitá também pretende ser multiplataforma, funcionando bem em tudo, desde grandes computadores até pequenos celulares. O Trojitá é um programa autônomo, que não faz parte de uma suíte de "gerenciamento de informações pessoais".</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Prioritizuje efektivitu, rýchlosť a otvorené štandardy nad iné ciele. Trojitá sa tiež zameriava na mnohoplatformovosť a funkcie známe od veľkých desktopových počítačov po malé mobilné telefóny. Trojitá je samostatný program, nie súčasť balíka "správy osobných informácií".</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Det prioriterar effektivitet, snabbhet och öppna standarder jämfört med andra mål. Trojitá har också målsättningen att hantera flera plattformar, och fungerar bra på allt från stora skrivbordsdatorer till små mobiltelefoner. Trojitá är ett fristående program, inte del av någon programsvit för "personlig informationshantering".</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Основними пріоритетами під час розробки програми є ефективність, швидкість роботи та використання відкритих стандартів. Крім того, Trojitá може працювати на багатьох платформах: від великих стаціонарних комп’ютерів до малих кишенькових телефонів. Trojitá є окремою програмою, а не частиною якогось комплекту для керування особистими даними.</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxIt prioritizes efficiency, speed and open standards above other goals. Trojitá also aims to be multi-platform, and functions well on everything from big desktop computers to small cellphones. Trojitá is a stand-alone program, not part of a "personal information manager" suite.xx</p>
    <p>What could make Trojitá interesting for you:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">ما قد يجعل تروجيتا مشوّقًا لك:</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Šta interesantno Trojitá može uraditi za vas:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">Què us podria fer el Trojitá interessant:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">Què vos podria fer el Trojitá interessant:</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Hvad der kunne gøre Trojitá interessant for dig:</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Τι θα μπορούσε να κάνει την Trojitá ενδιαφέρουσα για εσάς:</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">What could make Trojitá interesting for you:</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">Qué puede hacer a Trojitá interesante para usted:</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Miksi Trojitá voisi kiinnostaa sinua:</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">Trojitá podería interesarlle polo seguinte:</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Ecco cosa ti può rendere interessante Trojitá:</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">Trojitá의 특징적인 기능:</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Wat zou Trojitá voor u interessant kunnen maken:</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Co może cię zainteresować w Trojitá:</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O que poderá tornar o Trojitá interessante para si:</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">O que pode tornar o Trojitá interessante para você:</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Čo môže byť pre vás zaujímavé na Trojitá:</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Vad som skulle kunna göra  Trojitá intressant för dig:</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Можливості, які можуть зацікавити вас у Trojitá:</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxWhat could make Trojitá interesting for you:xx</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Very fast and robust IMAP core</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">نواة IMAP متينة وسريعة جدًّا</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Veoma brza i snažna IMAP jezgra</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">Un cor IMAP molt ràpid i robust</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">Un cor IMAP molt ràpid i robust</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Hurtig og robust IMAP-kerne</li>
      <li xml:lang="de">Sehr schneller und robuster IMAP-Kern</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Πολύ γρήγορος και σταθερός IMAP πυρήνας</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">Very fast and robust IMAP core</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">Un núcleo IMAP muy rápido y robusto</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Hyvin nopea ja vakaa IMAP-ydin</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">O núcleo de interacción con IMAP é moi rápido e robusto.</li>
      <li xml:lang="hu">Nagyon gyors és robusztus IMAP-mag</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Nucleo IMAP molto veloce e robusto</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">매우 빠르고 안정적인 IMAP 코어</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Erg snelle en robuuste IMAP-kern</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Bardzo szybki i zwinny rdzeń IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">Núcleo de IMAP muito rápido e robusto</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">Núcleo de IMAP muito rápido e robusto</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Veľmi rýchle a robustné jadro IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Mycket snabb och robust IMAP-kärna</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Дуже швидке і надійне ядро для обробки даних IMAP.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxVery fast and robust IMAP corexx</li>
      <li>Standards compliance is a design goal</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">الامتثال للمعايير هو هدف التّصميم</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Standardna usklađenost je cilj dizajna</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">El compliment dels estàndards és un objectiu en el disseny</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">El compliment dels estàndards és un objectiu en el disseny</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Standardoverholdelse er et designmål</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Η συμμόρφωση με τα πρότυπα είναι σχεδιαστικός στόχος</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">Standards compliance is a design goal</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">La conformidad con los estándares es un objetivo de su diseño</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Suunniteltu tavoitteenaan standardinmukaisuus</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">Un dos piares do seu deseño é o cumprimento cos estándares.</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Conformità agli standard come obbiettivo di progettazione</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">표준 준수를 목표로 설계됨</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Voldoen aan standaarden is een ontwerpdoel</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Zgodność ze standardami jest celem projektowym</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">A conformidade com as normas é um objectivo de desenho</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">A conformidade com os padrões é um objetivo do projeto</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Podpora štandardov je cieľom dizajnu</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Att följa standarder är ett konstruktionsmål</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Сумісність зі стандартами, яка є однією з основних цілей розробників.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxStandards compliance is a design goalxx</li>
      <li>On-demand message list and body part loading ("lazy loading")</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">قائمة رسائل على الطّلب وتحميل جزئيّ للمتن ("تحميل كسول")</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Lista poruka na zahtjev i učitavanje dijela tijela ("lijeno učitavanje")</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">Llista els missatges en demanar-ho i carrega la part del cos («càrrega retardada»)</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">Llista els missatges en demanar-ho i carrega la part del cos («càrrega retardada»)</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Indlæsning af brevliste og brevkrop efter behov ("doven indlæsning")</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Κατ' απαίτηση λίστα μηνυμάτων και φόρτωση κειμένου («καθυστερημένη φόρτωση»)</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">On-demand message list and body part loading ("lazy loading")</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">Lista de mensajes bajo demanda y descarga de partes de su contenido («descarga relajada»)</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Viestiluettelojen ja -runkojen lataus vain tarvittaessa (”laiskasti”)</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">Non carga a lista de mensaxes nin os corpos das mesmas ata que se solicita («carga preguiceira»).</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Elenco dei messaggi e caricamento del corpo del messaggio su richiesta («lazy loading»)</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">필요할 때 메시지 목록과 본문 불러오기("늦은 불러오기")</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Laden van berichtlijst en inhoud van berichten op aanvraag ("lui laden")</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Wczytywanie spisu wiadomości i ich treści na żądanie ("leniwe wczytywanie")</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">Carregamento da lista de mensagens e das componentes das mensagens a pedido ("carregamento posterior")</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">Carregamento do conteúdo e da lista de mensagens por solicitação ("carregamento posterior")</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Zoznam správ na požiadanie a načítavanie časti tela ("lenivé načítavanie")</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Inläsning av brevlista och innehåll vid behov ("lat inläsning")</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Завантаження списку та тексту повідомлень на вимогу («відкладене завантаження»).</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxOn-demand message list and body part loading ("lazy loading")xx</li>
      <li>Offline IMAP support</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">دعم IMAP بلا إنترنت</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Podrška za izvanmrežni IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">Permet IMAP desconnectat</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">Permet IMAP desconnectat</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Understøttelse af offline-IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="de">Unterstützung für Offline-IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Εκτός δικτύου υποστήριξη IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">Offline IMAP support</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">Uso de IMAP sin conexión</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Verkottoman IMAPin tuki</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">Compatibilidade con IMAP sen conexión.</li>
      <li xml:lang="hu">Kapcsolat nélküli IMAP-támogatás</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Supporto fuori linea IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">오프라인 IMAP 지원</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Ondersteuning van offline IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Obsługa IMAP bez sieci</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">Suporte para IMAP desligado</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">Suporte para IMAP desconectado</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Offline podpora IMAP</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Nerkopplat IMAP-stöd</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Підтримка роботи з IMAP у автономному режимі.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxOffline IMAP supportxx</li>
      <li>Support for bandwidth-saving mode aimed at mobile users with expensive connection</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">دعم وضع حفظ عرض النّطاق الّذي يستهدف مستخدمي الهاتف ذوي الاتّصال الغالي</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Podrška za režim snimanja propusnosti ciljan za korisnike mobilnih uređaja za skupom konekcijom</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">Permet el mode d'estalvi de l'amplada de banda destinat als usuaris de mòbils amb una connexió cara</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">Implementa el mode d'estalvi de l'amplada de banda destinat als usuaris de mòbils amb una connexió cara</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Understøttelse af båndbreddebesparende tilstand til mobile brugere dyre forbindelser</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Υποστήριξη λειτουργίας μείωσης της ευρυζωνικής κατανάλωσης για χρήστες κινητών με ακριβές συνδέσεις</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">Support for bandwidth-saving mode aimed at mobile users with expensive connection</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">Modo de ahorro de ancho de banda dirigido a usuarios de móviles con conexiones caras</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Tuki kaistansäästötilalle ajatellen mobiilikäyttäjiä, joille verkkoyhteys on kallis</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">Dispón dun modo de aforro de ancho de banda, pensado para usuarios de teléfonos móbiles para os que a conexión a internet resulta custosa.</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Supporto della modalità per il risparmio della banda, con lo sguardo rivolto agli utenti mobili con connessioni dispendiose</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">모바일 사용자를 위한 대역폭 절약 모드</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Ondersteuning voor bandbreedte besparende modus gericht op mobiele gebruikers met een dure verbinding</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Obsługa trybu oszczędzania przesyłu skierowana dla użytkowników mobilnych z kosztowym przyłączem do sieci</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">Suporte para o modo de poupança da largura de banda, destinado a utilizadores móveis com ligações caras</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">Suporte para o modo de economia de largura de banda, destinado a usuário de aparelhos móveis com conexões caras</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Podpora pre režim šetrenia pásma zameraná na mobilných používateľov s drahým pripojením</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Stöd för bandbreddsbesparande läge avsett för mobila användare med dyra anslutningar</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Підтримка режиму економії потужностей каналу обміну даними. Корисна для користувачів мобільного інтернету з дорогим тарифом.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxSupport for bandwidth-saving mode aimed at mobile users with expensive connectionxx</li>
      <li>IMAP over SSH -- instead of going over an SSL socket, the server could be accessed via SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">IMAP عبر SSH -- بدلًا من الاتّصال عبر مقبس SSL، يمكن النّفاذ إلى الخاوم عبر SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">IMAP prije SSH -- umjesto ići preko SSL priključka, serveru se može pristupiti preko SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">IMAP a través de SSH: en comptes d'anar a través d'un sòcol de SSL, el servidor pot accedir a través de SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">IMAP a través de SSH: en comptes d'anar a través d'un sòcol de SSL, el servidor pot accedir a través de SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">IMAP over SSH -- i stedet for at gå over en SSL-sokkel, kan serveren tilgås via SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">IMAP πάνω από SSH -- αντί πάνω από SSL υποδοχή, η πρόσβαση στο διακομιστή γίνεται με SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">IMAP over SSH -- instead of going over an SSL socket, the server could be accessed via SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">IMAP sobre SSH: en lugar de usar una conexión SSL, se puede acceder al servidor usando SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">IMAP SSH:n yli – SSL-pistokkeen käytön sijaan palvelimeen voidaan ottaa yhteys SSH:n avulla</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">Pode acceder ao servidor mediante SSH en vez de empregar un sócket SSL.</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">IMAP su SSH -- anziché lavorare su un socket SSL, al server si può accedere tramite SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">IMAP over SSH -- SSL 소켓 대신 SSH를 통하여 서버에 접근할 수 있습니다</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">IMAP over SSH -- in plaats van over een SSL-socket, de server kan bereikt worden via SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">IMAP przez SSH -- zamiast przesyłania przez gniazdo SSL, do serwer można się dostać przez SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">IMAP sobre SSH -- em vez de seguir por um 'socket' de SSL, o servidor poderá ser acedido através de SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">IMAP sobre SSH -- em vez de seguir por um socket SSL, o servidor pode ser acessado através de SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">IMAP cez SSH - namiesto prechodu cez SSL soket, na server je možné pristupovať cez SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">IMAP via SSH: Istället för att gå via ett SSL-uttag, kan servern kommas åt via SSH</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">IMAP через SSH — замість пропускання даних через сокет SSL, програма може отримувати доступ до сервера за допомогою SSH.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxIMAP over SSH -- instead of going over an SSL socket, the server could be accessed via SSHxx</li>
      <li>Safe and robust dealing with HTML mail</li>
      <li xml:lang="ar">تعامل مع بريد HTML متين وآمن</li>
      <li xml:lang="bs">Sigurno i čvrsto poslovanje sa HTML mail-om</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca">Manté un tracte segur i robust amb el correu HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="ca-valencia">Manté un tracte segur i robust amb el correu HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="da">Sikker og robust håndtering af HTML-e-mails</li>
      <li xml:lang="de">Sicherer und robuster Umgang mit HTML-E-Mails</li>
      <li xml:lang="el">Ασφαλής και σταθερή ανταπόκριση με μηνύματα σε HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="en-GB">Safe and robust dealing with HTML mail</li>
      <li xml:lang="es">Uso seguro y robusto de correo en HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="fi">Turvallinen ja luotettava HTML-viestien käsittely</li>
      <li xml:lang="gl">A súa xestión de mensaxes HTML é segura e robusta.</li>
      <li xml:lang="it">Gestione sicura e robusta della posta HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="ko">안전한 HTML 메시지 처리</li>
      <li xml:lang="nl">Veilig en robuust werken met HTML-e-mail</li>
      <li xml:lang="pl">Szybkie i zwinne radzenie sobie z pocztą HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt">Tratamento seguro e robusto de correio por HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="pt-BR">Tratamento seguro e robusto de e-mail HTML</li>
      <li xml:lang="sk">Bezpečná a robustná práca s HTML mailom</li>
      <li xml:lang="sv">Säker och robust hantering av HTML-brev</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Безпечна і надійна обробка поштових повідомлень у форматі HTML.</li>
      <li xml:lang="x-test">xxSafe and robust dealing with HTML mailxx</li>
    </ul>
  </description>
  <url type="homepage">http://trojita.flaska.net/</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://bugs.kde.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=trojita&amp;format=guided</url>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>http://trojita.flaska.net/img/2016-03-22-trojita-home.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Excessively quoted text is automatically collapsed</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="ca">El text citat excessivament es col·lapsa</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="ca-valencia">El text citat excessivament es col·lapsa</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="el">Το υπέρμετρο κείμενο σε παράθεση συμπτύσσεται αυτόματα</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="en-GB">Excessively quoted text is automatically collapsed</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="es">El texto citado en exceso se contrae automáticamente</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="gl">Os textos con demasiadas comiñas recóllese automaticamente.</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="it">Il testo eccessivamente citato viene automaticamente compresso</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="nl">Een grote hoeveelheid aangehaalde tekst wordt automatisch ingeklapt</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pl">Długi tekst cytowany jest samoczynnie zwijany</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pt">O texto citado em excesso é fechado automaticamente</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pt-BR">O texto citado em excesso é fechado automaticamente</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="sv">Överdrivet citerad text dras automatiskt ihop</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="uk">Автоматичне згортання значних фрагментів цитованих повідомлень.</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="x-test">xxExcessively quoted text is automatically collapsedxx</caption>
      <image>http://trojita.flaska.net/img/2016-03-22-quote-collapsing.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Encrypted and signed e-mail is supported, with status given in plain English</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="ca">Funciona amb correu electrònic encriptat i signat, amb l'estat indicat en anglès</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="ca-valencia">Funciona amb correu electrònic encriptat i signat, amb l'estat indicat en anglés</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="el">Υποστήριξη υπογεγραμμένων μηνυμάτων· η κατάσταση εμφανίζεται σε ανεπεξέργαστο κείμενο στην Αγγλική γλώσσα.</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="en-GB">Encrypted and signed e-mail is supported, with status given in plain English</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="es">Permite el uso de correo electrónico cifrado y firmado, con el estado dado en inglés sin formato</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="gl">Compatíbel con mensaxes cifradas e asinadas, co estado indicado con texto.</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="it">È supportata la posta elettronica cifrata e firmata, con lo stato indicato in inglese</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="nl">Versleutelde en ondertekende e-mail wordt ondersteund, met status gegeven in gewoon Engels</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pl">Obsługa szyfrowanej i podpisanej poczty wraz ze stanem podawanym w prostym angielskim</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pt">O e-mail encriptado e assinado é suportado, sendo o seu estado indicado em Inglês simples</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="pt-BR">Há suporte para e-mail criptografado e assinado, com status indicado em inglês simples</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="sv">Krypterade och signerade brev stöds, med status angiven på vanlig svenska</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="uk">Підтримка шифрування та підписування повідомлень із визначенням стану англійською.</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="x-test">xxEncrypted and signed e-mail is supported, with status given in plain Englishxx</caption>
      <image>http://trojita.flaska.net/img/2016-03-22-trojita-signature-missing-key.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <project_group>KDE</project_group>
  <provides>
    <binary>trojita</binary>
    <binary>be.contacts</binary>
  </provides>
</component>
